Guide to the Mas Yebra family correspondence
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mas Yebra family correspondence
1936-1940
MS 2101
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
.21
(1 box)
Correspondence of the Mas Yerba family, a prominent political family in Barcelona. The correspondence includes one hundred thirty-three letters exchanged among the family members and their associates during the Spanish Civil War. Also includes a small amount of the family's legal and financial papers.
Mas Yebra family
Mas Yebra, Juan Adolfo
Scope and Contents
Correspondence of the Mas Yerba family, a prominent political family in Barcelona. The correspondence includes one hundred thirty-three letters exchanged among the family members and their associates during the Spanish Civil War. Also includes a small amount of the family's legal and financial papers.
Correspondents include Adolfo Mas Yebra, a politician, his wife, Victoria, and their children, Luis Mas Yebra, Juan Antonio Mas Yebra, and Victoria Mas Yebra. Luis and Juan Antonio Mas Yebra each served in the Spanish Civil War, one for the Nationalists and one for the Republic. The correspondence also includes letters from Luis Mas Yebra to Monserrat (Montse) Mas Yebra, his wife, and letters to Victoria Mas Yebra from her parents, other family members, and friends. Juan Antonio served with an engineering corps and wrote letters to his parents from Lleida (Lerida) and Puebla de Castro, 1927 and 1938. Luis served as a major in the cavalry and wrote letters to his parents, wife, and sister from the front lines.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Librarian for the Latin American and Iberian Collections. Purchased by the Librarian for the Latin American and Iberian Collections from Kevin Jackson, 2017.
Biographical / Historical
Juan Adolfo Mas Yebra was born in Barcelona in 1850 and died there in 1942. He was a politician, and he and his wife, Victoria, had at least three children, including Juan Antonio Mas Yebra, Luis Mas Yebra, and Victoria Mas Yebra.
Luis and Juan Antonio Mas Yebra each served in the Spanish Civil War; Juan Antonio served with an engineering corps, and Luis served as a major in the cavalry. Luis Mas Yebra married Monserrat (Montse) Mas Yebra.
From Els Governs de la Ciutat de Barcelona (1875-1930): Eleccions, Partits I Regidors. Diccionari Biografi by Celia Canellas Julia and Rosa Toran Belver, his biography is as follows: Advocat, secretari de la SA Tibidabo, creada per impulsar la urbanitzacio i construccio del parc. Propietari important a Sant Gervasi, a Cornella i a Fogards de Tordera. Vicepresent de la Comissio d'Eixample de l'Ajuntament, president de la Cambra Oficial de la Propietat Urbana (1940), vocal del Foment del Treball (1900), secretari de l'Ateneu Barcelones (1891) i de La Cambra de Comerc (1908). Col-laborador del Diario de Barcelona despues de la Guerra Civil. Fundador a Barcelona del Partiti Conservador, de la Union Monarquica Nacional i del la Union Patriotica. R Distr. Universitat 1891. Conservador. He also wrote for La Reforma in Barcelona in 1898.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into groupings for each family member. Within those groupings, correspondence is sorted into incoming and outgoing groupings.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Mas Yebra family; Mas Yebra, Juan Adolfo
- Adolfo and Victoria Mas Yebra
  - Incoming
    - Letters to Adolfo Mas Yebra from friends, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing
    - Letters from Adolfo to others, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Victoria Mas Yebra, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Juan Antonio Mas Yebra
  - Letters to Adolfo Mas Yebra, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Luis Mas Yebra
  - Outgoing
    - Letters to Monserrat Mas Yebra, 1938- (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Adolfo Mas Yebra, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Victoria Mas Yebra, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incoming
    - Letters from friends, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Victoria Mas Yebra
  - Outgoing
    - Letters to Adolfo Mas Yebra, 1938? (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters to her brother, 1938? (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incoming
    - Letters from family and friends, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Legal and financial family papers, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)